{"tossups": [{"question": "One member of this family wrote the work<em> War or Peace</em>, which promoted liberation as an alternative to containment. One member of this family was a director of United Fruit at the same time that another member, a former attorney for that company, advised the president to launch the overthrow of Jacopo Arbenz in Operation PBSUCESS. The latter member of this family organized SEATO and developed the strategy of \u201cmassive retaliation\u201d for the Eisenhower administration. For ten points, name this family of CIA director Allen and Secretary of State John Foster, the latter of whom names an international airport in Washington, DC.", "answer": "<b> Dulles</b> (accept John Foster<b> Dulles</b>, or Allen<b> Dulles</b>, or Washington<b> Dulles</b> International Airport)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One leader of a kingdom centered at this city was executed at Castello de Pizzo after an ill-advised expedition that ended at the Battle of Tolentino; that man was Joachim Murat. The Battle of Cerignola confirmed Bourbon Spanish rule of this city, which was abandoned just before the Battle of the Volturnus. A kingdom with capital at this city was ended at the Siege of Gaeta. The Sicilian Vespers removed Sicily from the control of this city, which was targeted by the Expedition of a Thousand. For ten points, name this southern Italian city, the capital of the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies.", "answer": "<b> Naples</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "During this war, Mickey Marcus built a supply route out of Hulda whose name was inspired by an earlier supply route out of Burma. After the last battle in this conflict, a handmade flag called the Ink Flag was raised. An armistice to end this war was negotiated by Ralph Bunche, who took the position of UN mediator after Folke Bernadotte was assassinated by the terrorist group Lehi. As a result of this war, Egypt occupied the Gaza Strip and their opponent expanded beyond the Partition Plan\u2019s boundaries. For ten points, name this war in which Israel repelled an invasion by its neighbors right after it declared independence.", "answer": "<b> First Arab-Israeli</b> War (or<b> Arab-Israeli</b> War of<b> 1948</b>; or<b> Israeli War of Independence</b>; or<b> Al-Nakba</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A<em> Time</em> magazine article titled \u201cThe Price of Optimism\u201d sarcastically referred to this body of water as\u201csome river\u201d in the same year that Mayor Carl Stokes held a press conference on its shores. A 1969 article misleadingly used a 1952 photo of a destroyed tugboat on this river to support the claims that it was\u201cchocolate-brown, bubbling with subsurface gases.\u201d It is best known for spurring numerous environmental laws after it caught on fire in June 1969. For ten points, name this Ohio river that feeds Lake Erie.", "answer": "<b> Cuyahoga</b> River", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This work begins with a discussion of mbari, muhiriga, and riika, or family, clan and age group. This work discusses its subject\u2019s system of land tenure and discusses the Wakamba and Maasai in addition to its subject. This essay collection, which describes its author\u2019s ethnicity\u2019s contact with colonialism, was written for an anthropology seminar taught by Bronislaw Malinowski, who wrote its preface. For ten points, name this book by Jomo Kenyatta about his native country\u2019s Kikuyu people.", "answer": "<b> Facing Mount Kenya</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Anthropology"}, {"question": "One monument from this empire was displayed at the Porta Capena as a spoil of war. Saint Frumentius is credited with Christianizing this empire, which accepted Muslim refugees in the First Hijrah. A major expansion of this empire occurred after it conquered the Himyarite Kingdom under Kaleb. This empire was conquered by Gudit, who established the Zagwe dynasty. The Ark of the Covenant was supposedly brought to the capital city of this empire, though more real artifacts of this empire include many stone stelae [steel-ay]. The Queen of Sheba supposedly lived in, for ten points, what early kingdom in what is now Ethiopia?", "answer": "<b> Axum</b>ite Kingdom (or<b> Aksum</b>ite Kingdom; accept empire, etc. for kingdom)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Description acceptable. The subject of this event ominously noted \u201cIf someone has decided to drown, it is no longer possible to save them,\u201d rather than choose between saving either of two world leaders. The 2016 iteration of this event, the 14th overall, opened with an oblique reference to a \u201cpothole fairy\u201d and resulted in road crews being immediately sent to Omsk. This event usually takes several hours, and the content of the event is believed to be vetted before hand, though the Kremlin Press Secretary denies that. For ten points, name this annual event in which citizens can immediately pass their concerns on to a certain head of state.", "answer": "<b> Direct Line</b> with Vladimir Putin (accept descriptions of \u201cthe<b> TV show</b> in which Russians <b>call</b> (or<b> e-mail</b> or otherwise communicate with), asking questions for Vladimir<b> Putin</b>\u201d)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "In this location, Kolgrim was accused of using sorcery to seduce the wife of Torgrim; he was burned at the stake after his trial at a<em> thingstead</em> in the city of Gardar, where Norse settlers established a bishopric in 1126. Claus Paarss founded a fort at Godt-Haab in this location. The Brattahild was Erik the Red\u2019s estate on this island, whose name he devised as a marketing ploy. For ten points, name this largest non-continental island in the world, home to a country whose government system continues to include some Danish control.", "answer": "<b> Greenland</b> or<b> Kalaallit Nunaat</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this year, Maryland senator Charles Mathias criticized his party\u2019s drift towards radicalism and considered a primary run. John Tower was chosen to manage one candidate\u2019s campaign at his party\u2019s nominating convention in this year, only to not be chosen as a delegate after his candidate lost Texas. This year was the most recent in which no candidate won enough delegates to automatically become the nominee. For ten points, name this year in which the Republican convention resulted in Gerald Ford defeating Ronald Reagan, only to lose the general election to Jimmy Carter.", "answer": "<b> 1976</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s campaign manager Stephen Dorsey was implicated in the Star Routes scandal, leading to investigation by his attorney general Wayne MacVeagh. This man\u2019s choice of William Robertson to replace Edwin Merritt to be Collector of the Port of New York brought this man into conflict with pro-patronage figures like Senator Roscoe Conkling. For ten points, name this president assassinated in 1880 by Charles Guiteau, thus promoting Grover Cleveland to become president.", "answer": "James Abram<b> Garfield</b> <b>Second Quarter</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "At a protest opposing the visit of Mohammed Reza Shah Pahlavi in this year, Freie Universitant Berlin students Benno Ohnesorg was shot by police, leading to the formation of the 2 June Movement. In this year, students from the University of Rome, Sapienza had a skirmish with police officers in the Battle of Valle Giulia. A protest in May of this year by Sorbonne students led to a national crisis that culminated in Charles de Gaulle feeling the country. For ten points, name this year whose student protests helped lead to liberalization movements like Prague Spring.", "answer": "<b> 1968</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "On an incline in this competition, John Kelley gave Ellison Brown a pat on his shoulder, leading to Brown to come back and win it in 1936. Rosie Ruiz attempted to cheat in this competition by bursting out of a crowd. For ten points, name this oldest annual marathon in the U.S., whose finish line on Boylston Street was attacked by the Tsarnaev brothers\u2019 bombings in 2013.", "answer": "<b> Boston Marathon</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The poem \u201cZadonschina\u201d wrongly catalogued the numerical strength of the two sides in this battle. This battle hung upon whether or not Mikhail Brenok could draw enough enemy fire. Jogaila failed to arrive in time for this battle that was preceded by the Battle of the Vozha. Oleg II of Ryazan proved to be a fickle ally in this battle that forced Mamai to retreat to Caffa. Though the victor of this battle became celebrated as \u201cDonskoy,\u201d the outcome soon became irrelevant, as Toktamysh reimposed Golden Horde rule upon Dmitri of Moscow. For ten points, name this 1380 victory for the Russians in their quest to throw off Mongol rule.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Kulikovo</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In a song about this thing, the singer has \u201ca pocket full of quarters...[he\u2019s] bringing everything he\u2019s made;\u201d that novelty hit by Buckner and Garcia is about a fever named for this game. Level 256 presents this game\u2019s kill screen, causing the maximum score to be 3,333,360, first achieved by Billy Mitchell. The <em>E.T.</em> flop and a horrible port of this game sunk the Atari 2600 and contributed to the video game market crash. Invulnerability and the ability to eat Inky, Pinky, Blinky, and Clyde are granted by power pellets in, for ten points, what classic arcade game whose title character is most of a yellow circle?", "answer": "<b> Pac-Man</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The cavalry of the losers in this battle were weakened by a glanders infection. One side in this battle reinforced the villages of Oberglau and Lutzingen. A month before this battle, the victors in this battle captured a key supply station at Schellenberg. Along with another commander, Eugene of Savoy defeated troops led by the Duc de Tallard, who was captured during this battle. For ten points, name this major victory for the Grand Alliance that knocked Bavaria out of the War of the Spanish Succession, after which the Duke of Marlborough named his country estate.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Blenheim</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A 2005 Supreme Court case ruled against Norwegian Cruise Lines, claiming that this law still applied to foreign ships in American water. The application of this law was broadened under George W. Bush, who signed an amendment defining \u201cmajor life activities\u201d. In the Barden case, the city of Sacramento was sued for non-compliance with this law in its sidewalks. This law established a standard of \u201creasonable accommodations\u201d for the title group. For ten points, name this 1990 U.S. legislation that mandated adaptations for handicapped persons.", "answer": "<b> Americans with Disabilities Act</b> or<b> ADA</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man strove to grant full employment to citizens over 16 in an act co-sponsored with Augustus Hawkins. This assistant director of the War Manpower Commission was one</b> <b>of the primary authors of the Civil Rights Act of 1964. This \u201cHappy (+)</b> <b>Warrior\u201d helped</b> <b>found the Democratic-Farmer-Labor party, which he supported when he was elected mayor of (*) </b> Minneapolis for a second time. As chaos enveloped the Chicago convention, Eugene McCarthy was snubbed in favor of, for ten points, what 1968 Democratic nominee who lost the general election to Richard Nixon?", "answer": "Hubert H.<b> Humphrey</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>The first chronicle about these people was written by an anonymous \u201cP called magister\u201dand describes an exodus from Dentumoger. These subjects of the</b><em><b> Illuminated Chronicle</b></em> <b>were partially led by (+)</b> <b>Lel and Sur in a battle in which they killed Conrad the Red.</b> <b>These people migrated westwards from Khazaria, explaining their Uralic language exclave, and (*) </b> Almos supposedly unified them to create their house of Arpad. For ten points, name these people, defeated at Lechfeld by Otto the Great, who were Christianized by their king, Saint Stephen.", "answer": "<b> Hungarian</b>s (or<b> Magyar</b>s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>One work originally created in this city now resides in Hampton Court Palace and is the most complete depiction of a Roman triumph. The victor of the Battle of Fornovo hailed from this city, whose wife, Isabella d\u2019Este, was an important patron of its arts. Cherubim</b> <b>look down from a di sotta di su oculus in a room in this city\u2019s (+)</b> <b>Castle of St. George.</b> <b>The Camera degli Sposi [day-lee spoh-see] in this city was painted by the same man who depicted a body lying on a (*) </b> marble slab in the<em> Dead Christ</em>. For ten points, name this North Italian city, home of Andrea Mategna.", "answer": "<b> Mantua</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>When this man refused to carry out an ambush recommended by an enemy double-agent, he was demoted to a common soldier. This man defeated a numerically superior force by choosing a narrow strait with strong currents that flowed in opposite directions every (+) three hours as the battlefield. He designed vessels that had a dragon\u2019s head that belched out smoke created from burning sulfur; those ships used by this man were covered in (*) </b>spiked iron plates. For ten points, name this naval commander who died at the Battle of Noryang as his turtle ships defeated Toyotomi Hideyoshi\u2019s invasions of Korea.", "answer": "<b> Yi</b> Sun-sin", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Joe Gedeon attempted to earn a reward by exposing this scandal, but because he knew in advance and came forward after it finished, he was punished instead. Eddie Cicotte [see-cot] was one of the few participants in this event to admit his involvement. Though Buck Weaver did not participate, his failure to turn in the perpetrators earned him equal punishment from (+) Kenesaw Mountain Landis. Arnold Rothstein probably organized this scandal, which provided $5,000 to (*) </b> Shoeless Joe Jackson. For ten points, name this gambling scandal that resulted in the Cincinnati Reds having no trouble winning the 1919 World Series.", "answer": "<b> Black Sox</b> scandal (accept descriptions of \u201cthe Chicago<b> White Sox intentionally losing the World Series</b>\u201d, with \u201cWorld Series\u201d not required in the description after it\u2019s mentioned; prompt if just \u201cChicago\u201d is given for the team involved; prompt on \u201cfixing the World Series\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>One side in this conflict called their raids \u201cspanil\u00b4e jidzy,\u201d or beautiful rides. Sigismund Korybut served as regent for Grand Duke Vytataus of Lithuania in one part of this conflict.</b> <b>The Battle of Kutna Hora in this conflict was the first recorded use of field (+)</b> <b>artillery.</b> <b>One side in this conflict experienced infighting between its Taborite and Ultraquist factions. Wagon forts were employed by the one-eyed (*)</b> Jan Zizka in this conflict, which was started by the First Defenestration of Prague. For ten points, name this conflict that was fought against followers of a certain Czech priest and reformer who was burned at the stake in 1415.", "answer": "<b> Hussite</b> Wars (accept<b> Bohemian</b> Wars; accept descriptions of uprising, revolt, etc. instead of war)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This leader converted to Islam in order to receive aid from Gaddafi, but converted back to Christianity three months later when the aid did not arrive. This leader was overthrown</b> <b>in the French led Operation (+)</b> <b>Barracuda, which restored David Dacko to power. This</b> <b>leader purportedly beat schoolchildren with his walking stick after they refused to buy uniforms adorned with his face. This leader, who spent a third of his country\u2019s budget on a lavish (*)</b> 1977 coronation as Emperor, was acquitted of cannibalism when put on trial. For ten points, name this dictator of the Central African Republic during the 1970s.", "answer": "Jean-Bedel<b> Bokassa</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>A response to one work by a member of this family was written by Robert Calef. One member of this family campaigned against the Declaration of Indulgence, leading him to petition the King after being accused of treason. One member of this family was told by</b> <b>his slave Onesimus about the value of (+)</b> <b>inoculation, causing both him and his father to</b> <b>support it. One man in this family described his role in the Court of Oyer and Terminer, including his acceptance of (*)</b> spectral evidence, in the book<em> Wonders of the Invisible World</em>. For ten points, give this name shared by a father and son pair of Puritan ministers named Increase and Cotton.", "answer": "<b> Mather</b> family (accept Cotton and/or Increase<b> Mather</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The United Kingdom deployed its National Barrier Asset to this city in July 2015, and a football match between Kurds and Afghans in 2002 in this city\u2019s Sangatte camp resulted in riots. Natacha Bouchart, the mayor of this city, threatened to (+) block its port in 2014 after the P&O docks were stormed. In March 2016, the southern half of a refugee camp derisively called \u201cThe Jungle\u201d in this city was demolished. The (*)</b> Eurostar tunnel is a popular route for migrants attempting to cross into Great Britain from, for ten points, what northern French city on the Strait of Dover?", "answer": "<b> Calais</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Both the Second Thomas Shoal and Mischief Reef in</b> <b>this body of water have been the site of military positions. The (+)</b> <b>Ocean Oil 981</b> <b>triggered a 2014 incident in this body of water, which is home to the Paracel Islands. The (*) </b> nine-dotted line describes one country\u2019s claims in this sea, which have been enforced with artificial islands. The Spratly Islands are in, for ten points, what highly disputed Asian body of water?", "answer": "<b> South China</b> Sea (or<b> West Philippine</b> Sea)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}], "bonuses": []}